<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[[khzānet al-mukense]]]></title>
  <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-07-03T17:04:50+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[darwish]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On 'Who Am I to You?' and 'Who Are You to Me?' and 'Who Am I?']]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2019/07/03/who-am-i-to-you/"/>
    <updated>2019-07-03T17:00:04+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2019/07/03/who-am-i-to-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One simple but profound observation I feel I finally understood from Bateson today is the following. In any kind of communication the question: who am I to you? who are you to me? is at stake.</p>

<p>And there is no escaping this, this is so even if the communication is ostensibly &lsquo;just&rsquo; about the transmission of information about something else. That is, the transmission of information is always, has to be, also transmission of information about the relationship.</p>

<p>Otherwise (if there is no transmission of information also about the relationship), then there can no be no transmission of information, even about something else, in such a way that this information can be interpreted, can make sense at all.</p>

<p>At least this is so for communication between mammals. But then, for human mammals, it has to be a very dangerous game.</p>

<p>The dog — she pretty much only communicates with me about the variations of our relationship and very little about anything else.</p>

<p>Even behaviors to the effect of &lsquo;I want to play frisbee&rsquo; or &lsquo;I like it so much when you dry me with a towel&rsquo; — it looks like it is about (it stands for, manifests) something else (&lsquo;tastes&rsquo;, forms of enjoyment) but it is fundamentally about a &ldquo;you and me in the world&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Whereas for human mammals, it becomes very hazardous precisely because they can transmit information apparently autonomous from the relationship (i.e. from the ongoing exchange), yet even that has to, and will, carry information about the relationship.</p>

<p>I can think of at least three variations of how it becomes gut-wrenching. One is when we think, in good faith, that we talk about something else, something autonomous from the state of the relationship, and we inadvertently destroy the relationship.</p>

<p>This one, the one variation I just mentioned, it&rsquo;s something that can and should be worked upon (tactfulness, I guess) although it will probably happen to everybody one day.</p>

<p>Another one is the communication of pain between, for example, relatives. As my friend Nabil says, &ldquo;to your mother, even if you&rsquo;re on the verge of dying, you must say &lsquo;I feel strong like a horse!&rsquo;&rdquo;.</p>

<p>The other one is when we feel a bit unclear about where or who we are, we think (or are told) that trying to articulate it in language will help, but it will not necessarily do that in fact since the &lsquo;who I am&rsquo; is always, has to be, a &lsquo;who I am to you&rsquo;.</p>

<p>I would guess that it is so even in a psychotherapist&rsquo;s office.</p>

<p>This is why, I guess, communication with and between nonhuman mammals can strike us as so poor and so rich, or so full, at the same time. They cannot seduce themselves into the &lsquo;who am I&rsquo; kind of communication, and the dark labyrinths it opens, it&rsquo;s always &lsquo;who am I to you&rsquo;, period.</p>

<p>This is probably an example of discovering the Mediterranean sea as the Spaniards say, or at least it&rsquo;s what I remember reading they say.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Worldliness]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2018/06/14/worldliness/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-14T12:06:50+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2018/06/14/worldliness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[…]</p>

<p>By onto-ethics of worldliness, I mean, for now, a broad but specific
register of the ethical life anchored in a sense, or hunch, that the
self&rsquo;s relation to the world could and should be more admirable, more
far-reaching, and more wittingly reciprocal, than it is in the present.
Such an ethics presupposes an original orientation to self and world
that does not see their consociation as fixed but rather apprehends both
of them as unfinished and co-emergent. It also entails the apprehension
of a tendency running counter to this orientation in the human self, a
disposition to be out of kilter with the world, or a comfort found in a
state of relative alienation from it.</p>

<p>To be sure, the type of incipient striving towards worldliness I am
painting here with broad strokes can be, and has been, interpreted,
intensified and socially absorbed through very diverse and at times
divergent configurations of ethical life. In the Euroamerican
philosophical tradition, many will associate the concept of worldliness
with the major and quite distinct elaboration it received in the
twentieth century in the thought and writings of Hannah Arendt (1958a,
1978). Worldliness is, in one of her commentators' words, &ldquo;what Arendt
prizes most&rdquo; (Kateb 1977: 142), that of which the ever increasing
impracticability informs her critical diagnosis of the modern age, and
that of which the restoration orients her political and moral theory.
For Arendt, worldliness anchors itself as the highest pursuit in the
existential condition of <em>natality</em>: the &ldquo;naked fact&rdquo; of one&rsquo;s
&ldquo;appearance&rdquo; into being, which presupposes an immanent power to appear
and thus also the &ldquo;appearingness&rdquo; of other beings recipients of my
appearance (1978: 19-23, 1958a: 175-181). Every living entity&rsquo;s
appearance, in this Arendtian sense, is an ontological event that makes
sensible in the present an as yet indeterminate future in which this
entity will have been seen, heard, and otherwise pulled &ldquo;out of the
darkness of sheltered existence&rdquo; by other entities that it will have
similarly grasped and engaged in various ways (1958a:
175-181). This material-semiotic &ldquo;play&rdquo; (1978: 22) of
appearances is what Arendt called &ldquo;the world,&rdquo; which thus emerges and
lies, in her formulation, &ldquo;in-between&rdquo; (<em>inter-esse</em>) the entities that
appear to each other.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Anniversary]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/10/08/an-anniversary/"/>
    <updated>2017-10-08T14:34:56+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/10/08/an-anniversary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/images/photos/papa.jpg" title="[title:&#34;&#34;]" alt="[title:&#34;&#34;]"></p>

<p>This is a picture of my father, François Perdigon, who died by taking his own life this week 26 years ago. The plump, wide-eyed puppy sitting on his lap is me at the age of 0. I&rsquo;m posting this here, including the manner of his death, for two reasons. One is that this year, now, is the last year that I pass this anniversary while still younger than he was when he decided to end his life — next year I will remember the manner of his death as the choice of a relative ever younger than I am — and there is an overwhelming sense of impending transformation, and vertigo (and a bit of fear) that goes with that, of a life-threshold for me, not unlike other life-passages (weddings, graduations, etc.) which are made more real, including to ourselves, through being ritually shared with others, on the web amongst other places. I&rsquo;m remembering Hannah, too: &ldquo;Compared with the reality which comes from being seen and heard, even the greatest forces of intimate life — the passions of the heart, the thoughts of the mind, the delights of the senses — lead an uncertain, shadowy existence unless and until they are transformed, deprivatized and desindividualized, as it were, into a shape to fit them for public appearance.&rdquo; The other reason is that, frankly, as I&rsquo;m reaching this old age, I am also growing tired and impatient with the etiquette of silence surrounding suicide within kinship, or the assumption that only traumatic or traumatized discourse can happen in its wake. Making it visible as I&rsquo;m doing now is brutal, but keeping silent about it is brutal too, and not just for the one who keeps silent. So here is a small experiment, in mourning and remembering. Surely there should be a way to celebrate the natality and passage through the world of even those whose final act speaks poorly of natality, of the world, and perhaps of themselves, the possibility of an effort to make them, still, ancestors rather than ghosts.</p>

<p>I still apologize if you found this post brutal. (It&rsquo;s good, at least, that I have this space to do that, rather than being tempted to write one of those ghastly French papa-maman novels that Deleuze abhorred so much.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Visitor in the Office]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/09/15/a-visitor-in-the-office/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-15T08:16:33+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/09/15/a-visitor-in-the-office</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/images/photos/visitor.jpg" title="[title:&#34;&#34;]" alt="[title:&#34;&#34;]"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We Hold Ourselves in Place...]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/03/01/we-hold-ourselves-in-place/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-01T16:54:19+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/03/01/we-hold-ourselves-in-place</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;We hold ourselves in place through the interactional texts we build with and through others, and in the shadow of institutions of force. To use language effectively, all subjects must be able to operate-if not consciously understand-the principles by which texts cohere as the same principles that allow for their reformation. In short, the subject must learn to rely for survival on her provisionality within any one unfolding discursive space and her displacement across discursive spaces as her means of survival. In doing so, she places herself in the human lot: Every day, without relief from birth to death, she will remake the here and now whether she likes it or not, whether she knows it or not, in the context of institutional threat and incitement.</p>

<p>To be sure, these institutions might seem a welcome external brace, a resting place&hellip;"</p>

<p>Povinelli, Elizabeth A. 2001. “Sexuality at Risk: Psychoanalysis Metapragmatically.” In <em>Homosexuality and Psychoanalysis</em>, edited by Tim Dean and Christopher Lane, 387–411. (p. 404)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bolboul]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/18/bolboul/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-18T12:51:30+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/18/bolboul</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/images/photos/bolboul.jpg" title="[title:&#34;&#34;]" alt="[title:&#34;&#34;]"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[7500 Years Ago]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/18/7500-years-ago/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-18T12:48:03+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/18/7500-years-ago</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/images/photos/dog.jpg" title="[title:&#34;&#34;]" alt="[title:&#34;&#34;]"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Ode to Joy]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/18/ode-to-joy/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-18T12:24:29+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/18/ode-to-joy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am buying an espresso at Abu Naji&rsquo;s, a coffee stand/minimarket on Bliss street. I have not showered because there was no hot water at home, and I am wearing a beanie and a buff that I use when hiking because it is very cold today. Ba'ash, the employee in charge of sandwiches who is Palestinian from Sabra tells me:</p>

<p>&ldquo;You look like Beethoven.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Which, as a matter of fact, is true.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s from one incarnation of the whiteman to the next I guess.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Immense Cosmos]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/16/an-immense-cosmos/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-16T12:03:42+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/16/an-immense-cosmos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;The capitalistic economy of the present day is an immense cosmos into which the individual is born, and which presents itself to him, at least as an individual, as an unalterable order of things in which he must live. It forces the individual, in so far as he is involved in the system of market relationships, to conform to capitalistic rules of action. The manufacturer who in the long run acts counter to these norms, will just as inevitably be eliminated from the economic scene as the worker who cannot or will not adapt himself to them will be thrown into the streets without a job.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Max Weber in <em>The Protestant Ethic</em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dasein, the Office Cat]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/16/dasein-the-office-cat/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-16T12:00:21+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/16/dasein-the-office-cat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/images/photos/dasein.jpg" title="[title:&#34;&#34;]" alt="[title:&#34;&#34;]"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unfair to Sheep]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/14/unfair-to-sheep/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-14T15:43:56+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/14/unfair-to-sheep</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/images/photos/sheep.jpg" title="[title:&#34;don't sell your mind&#34;]" alt="[title:&#34;don't sell your mind&#34;]"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pigeons]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/14/pigeons/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-14T10:08:10+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/14/pigeons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;Not very many kinds of other-than-human critters have convinced human skeptics that the animals recognize themselves in a mirror—a talent made known to scientists by such actions as picking at paint spots or other marks on one’s body that are visible only in a mirror. Pigeons share this capacity with, at least, human children over two years old, rhesus macaques, chimpanzees, magpies, dolphins, and elephants […] Pigeons passed their  first mirror tests in the laboratories of B. F. Skinner in 1981. In 2008, <em>Science News</em> reported that Keio University researchers showed that, even with  five- to seven-second time delays, pigeons did better at self-recognition tests with both mirrors and live video images of themselves than three-year-old human children. Pigeons pick out different people in photographs very well too, and in Professor Shigeru Watanabe’s Laboratory of Comparative Cognitive Neuroscience at Keio University, pigeons could tell the difference between paintings by Monet or Picasso, and even generalize to discriminate unfamiliar paintings from different styles and schools by various painters.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Haraway, Donna J. 2016. <em>Staying with the Trouble: Making Kin in the Chthulucene</em>. Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some 'No! No!' Must Be Mixed In]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/13/some-no-no-must-be-mixed-in/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-13T09:52:36+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/13/some-no-no-must-be-mixed-in</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>William James on will (in <em>Varieties of Religious Experience</em>):</p>

<p>&ldquo;When we drop abstractions and take what we call our will in the act, we see that it is a very complex function. It involves both stimulations and inhibitions; it follows generalized habits; it is escorted by reflective criticisms; and it leaves a good or a bad taste of itself behind, according to the manner of the performance. The result is that, quite apart from the immediate pleasure which any sensible experience may give us, our own general moral attitude in procuring or undergoing the experience brings with it a secondary satisfaction or distaste. Some men and women, indeed, there are who can live on smiles and the word “yes” forever. But for others (indeed for most), this is too tepid and relaxed a moral climate. Passive happiness is slack and insipid, and soon grows mawkish and intolerable. Some austerity and wintry negativity, some roughness, danger, stringency, and effort, some “no! no!” must be mixed in, to produce the sense of an existence with character and texture and power. The range of individual differences in this respect is enormous; but whatever the mixture of yeses and noes may be, the person is infallibly aware when he has struck it in the right proportion FOR HIM. This, he feels, is my proper vocation, this is the OPTIMUM, the law, the life for me to live. Here I find the degree of equilibrium, safety, calm, and leisure which I need, or here I find the challenge, passion, fight, and hardship without which my soul’s energy expires.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Very Short Description]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/12/the-shortest-path/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-12T18:43:04+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/12/the-shortest-path</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Ṣilat al-Raḥim : Kinship, Birth and the Pursuit of Worldliness in a Palestinian refugee community</em> (<em>SAR</em>) builds on a paradox that binds birth, kinship and worldliness for long-term refugees. Obligations between kin can and are often reflexively interpreted as reverberations of the gift and debt of an individual&rsquo;s birth or appearance into the world. The <em>thisness</em> of kinship ties, in this basic sense, presupposes the prior presence, and amenability, of a world into which to be born and dwell. Refugees, however, come into being with arts of governmentality that disjoin birth from the world. Citizenship laws typically minimize their share of the ordinary modes of practical involvement by way of which worldly reality, and worldly selves, are made to appear for full subjects of the state. <em>SAR</em> traces everyday events by way of which kinship ties acquire shape, substance and force as refractions of birth for Palestinian men and women divested, by law, of much of a world into which to appear, and it explores the paradoxical figurations of worldliness that such events and relations entail.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reclaim Our Sea]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/12/reclaim-our-sea/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-12T16:26:36+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2017/02/12/reclaim-our-sea</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/images/photos/reclaimoursea.jpg"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
