<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Worldliness | [khzānet al-mukense]]]></title>
  <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/categories/worldliness/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2020-02-27T11:04:15+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[darwish]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Worldliness]]></title>
    <link href="http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2018/06/14/worldliness/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-14T12:06:50+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://sylvaindarwish.github.io/blog/2018/06/14/worldliness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[…]</p>

<p>By onto-ethics of worldliness, I mean, for now, a broad but specific
register of the ethical life anchored in a sense, or hunch, that the
self&rsquo;s relation to the world could and should be more admirable, more
far-reaching, and more wittingly reciprocal, than it is in the present.
Such an ethics presupposes an original orientation to self and world
that does not see their consociation as fixed but rather apprehends both
of them as unfinished and co-emergent. It also entails the apprehension
of a tendency running counter to this orientation in the human self, a
disposition to be out of kilter with the world, or a comfort found in a
state of relative alienation from it.</p>

<p>To be sure, the type of incipient striving towards worldliness I am
painting here with broad strokes can be, and has been, interpreted,
intensified and socially absorbed through very diverse and at times
divergent configurations of ethical life. In the Euroamerican
philosophical tradition, many will associate the concept of worldliness
with the major and quite distinct elaboration it received in the
twentieth century in the thought and writings of Hannah Arendt (1958a,
1978). Worldliness is, in one of her commentators' words, &ldquo;what Arendt
prizes most&rdquo; (Kateb 1977: 142), that of which the ever increasing
impracticability informs her critical diagnosis of the modern age, and
that of which the restoration orients her political and moral theory.
For Arendt, worldliness anchors itself as the highest pursuit in the
existential condition of <em>natality</em>: the &ldquo;naked fact&rdquo; of one&rsquo;s
&ldquo;appearance&rdquo; into being, which presupposes an immanent power to appear
and thus also the &ldquo;appearingness&rdquo; of other beings recipients of my
appearance (1978: 19-23, 1958a: 175-181). Every living entity&rsquo;s
appearance, in this Arendtian sense, is an ontological event that makes
sensible in the present an as yet indeterminate future in which this
entity will have been seen, heard, and otherwise pulled &ldquo;out of the
darkness of sheltered existence&rdquo; by other entities that it will have
similarly grasped and engaged in various ways (1958a:
175-181). This material-semiotic &ldquo;play&rdquo; (1978: 22) of
appearances is what Arendt called &ldquo;the world,&rdquo; which thus emerges and
lies, in her formulation, &ldquo;in-between&rdquo; (<em>inter-esse</em>) the entities that
appear to each other.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>In the case of the human animal, the mediation of &ldquo;word and deed&rdquo; within
this interplay immensely amplifies the range and wealth of worlds it
holds <em>in potentia</em>, Arendt argued, at the same time as it extends and
deepens the &ldquo;disclosure&rdquo; of those who take part in it (including of
themselves to themselves). Such a potential and
intensification, however, are dependent for their actualization on the
availability of a shared &ldquo;space of appearance,&rdquo; that is, on the prior
scaffolding of a virtual structure fixed enough to house the
incorporation of an incommensurate plurality of words and deeds,
perspectives and aspects, wills and efforts, into an enduring common
world, instead of their dissipation into a swirl of
noise. <em>&lsquo;Worldly&rsquo;</em> is
thus the predicate of that which has achieved the relative consistency,
hardiness and endurance of a world spawned out of the play and mutual
refractions of the entities that appeared in it. But
worldliness also applies, by extension, to that which makes this
achievement possible in the first place, at least amongst speaking and
acting creatures, viz., a common commitment on their part to the reality
and sufficiency of the world that will have emerged between them.</p>

<p>Arendt found the practical and cultural conditions for such a commitment
lacking, undermined or even deliberately taken away from some under
modernity. A great deal of her work from <em>The Origins of
Totalitarianism</em> (1958b) onwards is dedicated to analyzing the &ldquo;atrophy
of the space of appearance&rdquo; (1958a: 209) in the modern age under a vast
array of forces that include capitalist expropriation, the
technoscientific shrinking of the earth, and the capture of the
political by the nation-state. The stateless refugee constitutes the
prototypical figure, in the genesis of this analysis, of &ldquo;a new kind of
human beings&rdquo; (1994: 111) who, being denied entry into a public realm
enclosed by national citizenship, are deprived of &ldquo;<em>a place in the
world</em> that makes opinions significant and actions effective&rdquo; (1958b:
296, emphasis added). The near equivalence that Arendt assumes between
the pursuit of worldliness and the semiosis of public life, her
assimilation and indeed at times willful containment of the former to
the latter, has for correlate that the ethical and political <em>telos</em> of
worldliness stands, for her, in awkward tension with kinship. In <em>The
Human Condition</em> in particular, Arendt asserts (rather than argues) that
the family <em>cannot</em> be a world &mdash; it cannot be the scene for seeing and
hearing others, and being seen and heard by them, in a manner that makes
it possible for &ldquo;worldly reality [to] truly and reliably appear&rdquo;
(1958a: 57). The household and neighborhood, in her view,
are milieus that can only allow for a mere replication of the same
perspective from which no worldly in-between could ever emerge. Yet
these pronouncements are at odds with other writings where Arendt
&ldquo;insists on the affirmation of all that she seems subsequently to
dismiss from the political space&rdquo; (Birmingham 2006: 71). In such
passages, and counter to the strict distinction between the <em>bios
politikos</em> and <em>zoe</em> championed in <em>HC</em>, the &ldquo;sphere of private life&rdquo; is
that which shelters and sustains, in the face of &ldquo;dumb hatred, mistrust
and discrimination,&rdquo; the &ldquo;dark background of mere givenness&rdquo; internal to
the event of appearance that carries within it and anchors the principle
of plurality and worldliness (1958b: 301).</p>

<p>A more contemporary proponent of an ethics of worldliness is Donna
Haraway, who makes explicit use of this very language and concept in a
manner that echoes Arendt&rsquo;s to name the kind of response that critical
social theory must contribute to formulate and bring about in the face
of ecological devastation (Haraway 2008). Worldliness, in Haraway&rsquo;s
writings, applies both to an existential (material-semiotic) condition
that grounds an ethical and political project of joint flourishing in
worlds that humans share and co-shape, in a robust sense, with other
kinds of lives, at the same time as it indicates the horizon of this
project. Worldly is something that one is, and something at the same
time that one has to <em>learn</em> to be (3) against depredatory habits of
living anchored in &ldquo;human exceptionalism,&rdquo; or the &ldquo;[fantastic] premise
that humanity alone is not a spatial and temporal web of interspecies
dependencies&rdquo; (11). Such a process of learning involves enriching and
intensifying &ldquo;attachment sites and sticky knots&rdquo; (296) that makes human
and other types of lives and worlds possible, and this, through the
cultivation of knowledge, respect and &ldquo;response-ability&rdquo; (88) across
species and kinds. Interestingly, and in contradistinction to Arendt&rsquo;s
equivocations, Haraway has taken to argue in her most recent writings
that the pursuit of worldliness in this anthropocenic sense amounts to
an urgent practice of learning to <em>&ldquo;make kin&rdquo;</em> not only within but also
across disparate orders of living (2015, esp. 161-162, 2016). Making
&ldquo;make kin!&rdquo; a slogan for better living in the midst of ecological system
collapse surely subjects the language of kinship to metapragmatic
&ldquo;stretch and recomposition&rdquo;: it entails a deliberate framework for
putting it to use in new contexts and with new relationalities as its
referents. But if this slogan presents itself to us with
any force, Haraway claims, it is also that it returns to, and taps into,
this language&rsquo;s &ldquo;deepest sense&rdquo;, a prior interpretation that connects
kinship with the worlding of worlds. &ldquo;Kin is an assembling
sort of word&rdquo; (162).</p>

<p>In the remainder of this essay, taking my cues from Haraway, Arendt and
the anthropologists of kinship whose recent works I channeled, I try to
further explore and conceptualize linkages between formations of kinship
and the ethics of worldliness in the ethnographic context of Palestinian
refugee camps in Lebanon in the mid-2000s.</p>

<p>Arendt, Hannah. 1958a. <em>The Human Condition</em>. Chicago: University of
Chicago Press.</p>

<p>&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;. 1958b. <em>The Origins of Totalitarianism</em>. Cleveland: Meridian
Books.</p>

<p>&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;. 1978. <em>The Life of the Mind. Volume I : Thinking</em>. Edited by
Mary McCarthy. New York: Harcourt Brace.</p>

<p>&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;. 1994. &ldquo;We Refugees.&rdquo; In <em>Altogether Elsewhere: Writers on
Exile</em>, edited by Marc Robinson, 110&ndash;19. Boston: Faber.</p>

<p>Birmingham, Peg. 2006. <em>Hannah Arendt and Human Rights : The Predicament
of Common Responsibility</em>. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</p>

<p>Haraway, Donna. 2008. <em>When Species Meet</em>. Minneapolis: University of
Minnesota Press.</p>

<p>&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;. 2015. &ldquo;Anthropocene, Capitalocene, Plantationocene,
Chthulucene: Making Kin.&rdquo; <em>Environmental Humanities</em> 6: 159&ndash;65.</p>

<p>&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;. 2016. <em>Staying with the Trouble: Making Kin in the
Chthulucene</em>. Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press.</p>

<p>Kateb, George. 1977. &ldquo;Freedom and Worldliness in the Thought of Hannah
Arendt.&rdquo; <em>Political Theory</em> 5 (2): 141&ndash;82.</p>

<p>[…]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
